computer okay wonderful we're back
recording thanks so much for the
conversation we just had part one and
now we're taking a little bit of a deep
dive into some of the things that I
learned from you and and also would love
to have your reflections on in terms of
my own learning and one I came a couple
of years ago when I was writing my book
designing regenerative cultures I came
across the work of a biologist and
systems theorist called John Stewart and
he described evolution in the way that
I'd not heard it described before but it
really made a lot of sense to me he said
that the general process of evolution is
a process of diversification and then
subsequent integration of that diversity
at higher levels of complexity and he
said that more often than not in the
long arc of evolution that reintegration
of diversity at higher levels of
complexity happens through collaborative
processes whether this is to nucleated
cells in one engulfing the other in
forming a nucleated cells the endless
symbiosis theory and what that made
possible in terms of multicellular
organism and most of higher life-forms
being based on nucleated cells and then
how that from multicellular organism to
social organism see everytime you get or
the complexity of ecosystems that the
process by which life creates conditions
conducive to life seems to be so much
more um symbiotic and Symphonic
altogether optimizing the whole system
then it is about competing individuals
one against the other I mean both hands
and so do you agree that we might have
in evolutionary theory and also in
education around biology and evolution
have somewhat over focused on
competition as a driving force in
evolution and have undervalued the ocean
of symbiosis and collaboration that
actually underlies that when you zoom
out and you take a systems view of life
absolutely absolutely but first let me
say that
I really like Stewart's way of
describing evolution and and the
emphasis on cooperation makes total
sense because it is actually implied in
the diversification if you understand
life as a network then biodiversity
means higher complexity of the network
more connections and since this living
network is a network of processes of
metabolic and cognitive processes and
ecological processes every new
connection can be seen as a cooperation
so collections are cooperations and and
greater diversity means more cooperation
or if the cooperation lacks of course it
means breakdown and then you have the
the situation like like we have in in
our political world where we have
prejudice in groups fighting each other
and and you know distinguishing between
us and panda me and the other that is
the lack of cooperation but nature non
human nature that doesn't work like that
it cooperates basically so so my one of
my great mentors in biology has been
Lynn Margulis the famous microbiologist
who really taught me that among many
things that there are three avenues of
evolution that the classical
neo-darwinian theory the the the modern
synthesis it's also called recognizes
only random mutations followed by
natural selection but random mutations
are only part of evolution bacteria can
mutate very far
and multiply very fast but they have
another way of changing the genome and
that is by horizontal gene transfer they
trade genes so they spill out the
bacterium will in you know day to day in
its day-to-day life it will spill out a
certain proportion of its of its genes
and other bacteria will absorb it and so
there's a constant trading of genes to
the extent that some microbiologists
think that one should not talk about
species of bacteria because the genome
is so fluid and always changing that you
can't define species so innocent just
briefly in a similar way I find that
when we talk about ourselves Homo
sapiens which is a bit of sapiens
sapiens which is slightly arrogant
compared to whom we're currently
performing and we are not one species we
are walking ecosystems the amount of gut
flora and and skin flora that we have
that maintain is a life and healthy we
actually have more non-human cells in
our bodies and on our bodies than we
have human cells so absolutely yes so so
the second Avenue evolution is the gene
trading and the third Avenue of
evolution is is something that lynn
margulis popularized and built a theory
around and that's symbiosis
so there are you know two organisms
living in close proximity to the extent
that they end up completely depending on
one another and forming a new organism
so for example the chloroplasts in plant
cells that contain the chlorophyll and
are essential for photosynthesis were
original originally individual bacteria
that invaded the cell and then you know
became comfortable there and collaborate
it cooperated with the plant cell so you
have these three avenues of evolution
genetics
random mutation which is not that random
either but let's not get into that
becomes too complicated so random well
let me just say that an organism can
control the amount of randomness the the
random mutation is based on a copying
error of the DNA and the error the
amount of error can be controlled by the
organism but that's a whole other story
so anyway you have random mutation gene
trading and sim buy or Genesis as
smuggles calls it now what happens then
is you have a new genome and that new
genome has to be integrated into its
environment into its cellular
environment into its tissue environment
and into the larger environment a
natural selection will see to it that
only the successful integration can
survive now this integration of a new
genome in its environment is a highly
ordered and very complex process you
know I remember spending hours with with
Lin one evening at the Cortona school
that Pierluigi Louise you organized late
at night where she explained to me how
genomes are integrated in the
environment and you know my head began
to swim it's very very complex so
evolution has random elements but
overall it is an ordered process it is a
complex process it is a cooperative
process and as we have come to
understand it is a cognitive process
because according to the so called
Santiago theory of cognition about which
I've written a lot the the the very
essential dynamics of self-organization
is cognitive so that's a very different
view of evolution from the sort of
lottery point
fuels new Darwinists yeah and you just
gave me the key for the next question
because I remember you and I'm gonna
paraphrase because I don't know the
exact quote I remember you saying
something I think it was even in the
turning point and which was that if you
follow the converging crises that we see
around the planet at the moment the
ecological crisis now you could say the
ecological and the climate crisis the
social crisis and social breakdown and
the ever faster cycles of economic
crisis and if you follow all these
rivers upstream you come to one single
source which is a crisis of perception
or crisis of consciousness and to some
extent the Santiago theory of cognition
is one of the first scientific theories
that overcomes part of that crisis of
consciousness that dualism between mind
and matter self and world nature culture
the way that we we tend to distinguish
things in a Cartesian framework rather
than pay attention through the dimension
of mind in what we are observing yeah I
did talk about the crisis of perception
I think in the turning point in the
early 1980s and I may have got that
phrase from hazel Henderson the radical
economist who is an old friend of mine
so what we're talking about here is a
very profound change of worldview that
has been happening over the last half
century and longer the change of
paradigms essentially from seeing the
world as a machine to understanding it
as a network and a network of course is
a pattern of relationships and therefore
in order to understand networks we need
to understand patterns and relationships
and that's what
systems thinking is all about and that's
why I call the the new paradigm a
systemic or system's view of the world
and so this has a profound effect on on
all our activities and endeavors
professionally and personally
because what we're dealing with in our
personal and professional lives is
usually living systems whether we talk
about the economy or education or
healthcare or management all that has to
do with life and so the profound change
from seeing life as a crock workers as a
machine to understanding it as a network
of processes and as a cognitive network
and this is now what the Santiago theory
developed by Humberto Maturana and
Francisco Varela at the University of
Santiago in in Chile
what this theory says is that the
dynamics of organization of
self-organization of living organisms or
any living systems is essentially a
cognitive process this is a great
expansion of the view of cognition
cognition is the self-organizing
activity of living systems so when when
an organism perceives something that
stimulus so that disturbance as matter
Anna calls it will enter the organism
and the organism will respond to it with
certain structural changes according to
its nature the environment triggers the
response triggers the structural changes
but doesn't determine them and the
organism actually cell
what to notice and what not to notice if
I understand them correctly there it's
almost because we talked earlier about
the kind of parallels of the wisdom
traditions to science and this what in
the Vedanta they call the first
distinction and is is actually the
organism observed like in in the
structural coupling between organism and
environment what we now call environment
actually becomes the environment the
organism becomes organism so it's this
first distinction of the boundary
between organism and environment that is
the beginning of that process of that
that's right
yes sorry I didn't want so so when we
adopt this view of seeing life around us
as cognitive cognitive systems and
therefore as intelligent this will
profoundly influence the way we deal
with our environment if the environment
really were a machine then the best way
to deal with it would be to control it
that's what you do when you drive your
car you need to control it otherwise you
get into trouble the way one deals with
the machine is you know to control it
but if the environment is a living
system a living being an intelligent
being then the best way to deal with it
is not by a domination and control but
by a dialogue and cooperation and
partnership and there's so much we can
learn from nature so rather than
controlling nature or rather then
extracting things from nature for our
use we can extract knowledge from nature
and can learn from nature because you
know natural systems have solved many of
the problems we are struggling
with you know millions of years ago
there's this whole movement of eco
design and biomimicry that you know
tries to learn from nature and copy
nature to design you know I attempted to
in terms of the languages because we're
talking about the upstream conception
change or the consciousness change the
way we used the word nature and you've
just done it yourself and Jeanine does
it but biomimicry it's learning from
nature when we say from we actually put
nature back out there again but of
course what we're really talking about
is that we as human beings are part of
that process and we learn as nature from
the wider community of life yeah yeah
that's right but but of course you know
when you when you interact with somebody
there are connections but there are also
differences you know I learned from you
and you learn from me and we both learn
from nature yeah as the wider context in
for me the so much about I mean to some
extent the Santiago theory also speaks
to what what is life and but the in the
work that I do with bringing in this
concept of regeneration as life as a
regenerative community to understand how
life we were talking about it earlier
these patterns of complexification also
then in local pockets need breakdown of
ossified structures that no longer serve
in order to unleash the possibility for
new connections and in in your book the
system's view of life you have to
subchapters one of them ask the question
what is life and then you also ask the
question what is death and I think that
the second part we often culturally add
two booing death as something negative
but in many ways good more than 200
years ago said and that death is life's
ingenious way to create plenty of life
so I would love for you to to speak
to that dynamic relationship between
life and death
and how that might inform us to
participate in that longer cycle more
wisely no yeah I didn't know this saying
of greater that's very beautiful and so
well of course the the central question
that I have been exploring for the last
thirty years is the question what is
light
you know the age-old question what is
life and so when you go around to
biology departments and ask the
professor's there what's your definition
of life then they tend to focus on the
structures of living systems so they
might say well the essential difference
between a rock and the plant is the fact
that a plant is made of cells all living
systems are either individual cells or
made of cells a rock is not made of
cells and within the cells there are
very large molecules macromolecules like
proteins lipids DNA RNA with a carbon
backbone and some and they don't exist
in nonliving systems and some biologists
might even say well life is a chemical
even organism it's a chemical system
made of DNA so all you have to do is
really look for DNA if you see DNA it's
alive if you don't see DNA it's not
alive well this sounds very simple but
it is flawed because dead organisms also
contain DNA when an organism dies the
DNA doesn't disappear it's just a
molecule and it stays there so the
difference between the living and the
dead organism or living and the
non-living organism
is the process of life is what poets and
philosophers for ages have called the
breath of life and in modern scientific
language the breath of life is called
metabolism this is something I learned
from also from Lynn Margulis she defines
metabolism as a constant flow of energy
and matter through a network of
processes of chemical reactions in a
cell for example which allows the
organism continually to continually
regenerate itself repair itself and
perpetuate itself so in this definition
of metabolism there are two aspects the
flow aspect and the network aspect and
my synthesis of this whole system's way
of life is essentially a synthesis
between the flow aspect in the network
aspect so the flow aspect was researched
and developed by Ilya Prigogine
in his concept of dissipative structures
of systems being continuously far from
equilibrium subject to constant flows of
energy and matter and then the network
aspect was developed by matter Anna and
Marella who discovered that the key
characteristic of these living networks
is that there are self generating self
producing self making and they coined
the Greek term which literally means
self making that's Otto poiesis
Otto polices so these autopoietic
networks continually regenerate
themselves replace their structures
transform their structures and
regenerate themselves and you must like
that very much
because you have written this book about
regenerative cultures
regeneration is a term that is has
become very popular lately you know
thanks partly to your work and so we can
say that if you really understand the
systemic nature of life in terms of Auto
Asaph that a living system is a
regenerative system that's the very
definition of life yeah I like life as a
planetary process is a regenerative
community and when you were saying in
pre-kg and I was reminded suddenly that
when when I first had a conversation
about with with Jim Lovelock at cha maha
college and about that first moment when
when he kind of got struck with the
first vision of of Gaia as as a
planetary process and he was actually
working on helping to design new
instruments for detecting life on Mars
he was at the Jet Propulsion
laboratories at the time and in the
office nextel data new data came in from
radio spectrometry or something of the
atmospheric compositions of all the
other planets and in his tea break he
just looked at his colleagues dataset
and he noticed something that really
struck him which was dead in all on all
the other planets in our solar system
there is a chemical equilibrium meaning
that all the reactions that can happen
have already happened and and the the
gases are in compositions that have
balanced each other out and then if you
look at Gaia there's a stock to say
equilibrium um that makes life possible
and and and he at that moment he
basically almost got himself out of a
job by basically saying we don't need to
design more instruments we don't need to
send anybody upset I can tell you that
there isn't any life there because the
the process of life is what creates the
disequilibrium yeah and you know eugene
would say because the earth is
dissipative structure and
and Venus and Mars are not dissipative
structures now Daniel do you know was
Lovelock way of Riga Sheen's work at
that time I actually don't know and I'm
about bad but in terms of the historic
do you know when prigogine did his work
because this insight is in the sixties
yeah yeah so I think they must have as
happens people have the same rush
because and madryn in Bateson you know
Bateson with its concept of mind as a
systems phenomenon and matter Anna with
you know this idea of cognition as as
the dynamics of self-organization but
let's let's go on to your ask me Bob
also and this part in our textbook is
actually about the Louise erode and what
he says is that life is a certain
pattern it's a pattern of
self-organization of self generation of
regeneration and death is the breaking
of that pattern but that pattern may
break all of a sudden when you know you
somebody has a car accident and dies on
the spot or a stroke or a heart attack
or what is more much more common the
pattern may break slowly and that's the
process of aging you know certain
collections no longer work or you know I
know from my experience as I'm getting
older my hearing is not what it used to
be you know my attention span is not
what it used to be of course we wear
glasses you know yeah I take naps in the
afternoon I don't have to I can survive
without a nap in the afternoon but I
really like it and I highly recommend
that it's my it's my grandmother's
recipe for success and she turned 103 so
so the slow breaking of this pattern of
connections is for aging is and
eventually resulting in tests and at the
end of your book like if you may because
but before before we go there I wanted
to UM pick up on that dimension of
breakdown or periodic disturbance in the
like if we zoom out from the kind of
individual focus on life and we really
look at life as a systemic phenomenon
across ecosystems that maintain
planetary health and the conditions
conducive to life for life on on the
planet M I sense that there's a lot of
discussion at the moment about are we in
collapse and is there already too late
and life itself teaches that at the edge
of chaos the system as it is at its most
creative because the rigidity of the
structures that have created the
imbalance also begin to break down and I
feel like that's exactly what's
happening right now around the globe we
see systems crumbling and it's it's
alarming and it's disconcerting and
withered we you also see evil monsters
of the past rear their ugly heads em as
people demagogues and try to use that
opportunity of multiple breakdowns for
their own benefits but ultimately the
positive take on that would be that
these breakdowns are actually part of
the systemic transformation that is now
really underway and and that that
actually is part of life's pattern to do
resume without reading absolutely
because something we haven't talked
about yet is the process of emergence
which is a key characteristic of life in
the system's fields right and this is
something that has been developed by
Ilya Prigogine and and to me
understanding the process of emergence
is probably the biggest achievement of
complexity theory and what we have
understood is that even though all live
organisms maintain themselves in a state
of balance in a state of homeostasis
every now and then they will encounter a
point of imbalance and at that point of
imbalance and prigogine described this
dynamic there is there is a disturbance
either from the environment or from the
inner workings of the organism and that
instead that disturbance gets sent
around feedback loops and goes around
and around and gets amplified as you
know there are two kinds of feedback
self-balancing feedback and self
amplifying feedback so it gets amplified
and amplified until the system as a
whole
reaches a state of crisis straight state
of imbalance technically known as
bifurcation point and it can then go in
different directions it will either
break down or more frequently will break
through to a new state of order and this
is what we are experiencing now in the
world at large there there is imbalance
there is crisis there is emergency and
hopefully we will be able to break
through to a new state of Ohio order
yeah that's exactly where I feel we're
at and the jury is still out whether
we're gonna make it but but Daniel I
want to come back to life and death and
that good quotation from Goethe that you
mentioned and that is is totally borne
out by by science because when you when
you think of living systems as
constantly renewing themselves and when
you think of this constant regeneration
as the
very essence of life and apply this say
to a human organism then we know that we
constantly renew and recycle ourselves
very rapidly in fact so the stomach
lining for instance you know changes
completely within 24 hours or something
like this and you know other other
tissues have a rapid turnover of cells
so this constant self renewal
is the very essence of life well if you
look at it from the point of view of the
cell it's a cycle of life and death so
what is life and death at one level is
the very essence of life at the higher
level and and that's a very deep insight
and I think this is what gorillas who
had many deep insights meant in this
this quotation comes from Goethe suffer
rhythms on nature which is something
that he wrote relatively late in life
where he really in an essence picked up
some of his learnings and it was
actually an older house Huxley's father
or grandfather when he got the
opportunity to write the foreword for
the first edition of nature he got two
pages and he he quoted Goethe for heart
for almost half or more than half of his
new pages and saying something along the
lines of long long after the
intellectual pursuits of the people that
were published in these in this journal
will be forgotten the vision of the poet
will remain and then then he basically
copies a section of of Goethe's
aphorisms on my child I'll send them to
you there they did they're curious
great thank you I I think what I'm gonna
do is I make you gonna stop the
recording again here and then we do a
third one if you if you still feel up
for it because it's okay so in in the
break now